they report on landing site is through
suggesting the death takeoff off-road
intestines will I fall in an expensive
basic reason here is dummy whatever is
triggered sales few segments on new
terrain
kgm just fired a missile at the BMW r12
hundred GS collateral damage significant
notably the Ducati Multistrada and zero
the sticker on here says 1290 super
adventure are it seems to power itself
with the mythical lc8 v-twin now some
people say this engine won the car in
2002 and also cut its teeth inside the
RCA Supersport race bike well sort of
anyway and then KTM constantly evolves
the elsi-8 so every encounter is going
to be different now this time like the
Super Duke we see its bore and Stroke
hollowed out to 1301 CCS it also makes
103 foot-pounds of torque and 160
horsepower this is now the most powerful
thing on earth with a 21-inch front
wheel cutter Hercules humanity is
carving out new terrain for KTM that
it's also eat again
ain't it stop please 160 horsepower does
not move dirt it moves the earth
let's take a step back and figure out
what in the hell we've discovered here
first glance tells me that the frame and
engine are descended from the old twelve
ninety now relabeled the super adventure
touring but the tank and wheel sizes are
from the eleven ninety R which was pure
adventure the headlight is totally alien
it's an LED so powerful that it has its
own radiator
a heatsink slash down the center in
order to cool the bulbs the wheels are
spoked
and tubeless alloys made stronger
because the old 1190 front used to taco
at the first sight of a rut I can
already see the 1190 guys buying these
and retrofitting most obvious new
features the giant smartphone on the
dashboard it's six and a half inches of
Gorilla Glass that means it won't
scratch even well then 1290 gets a few
crumbs of Earth on it smells now despite
what the puff-piece journalists say this
does reflect a very normal amount of
glare also I could feasibly put a rock
right through the 1298 shiny new iPad if
I were to drop the bike at just the
right angle is it just me or is this
bike alive it seems when the key is
within five feet making itself ready to
race or ready for a pint
it keeps an eye on its own tire
pressures it holds its own cruising
speed the 1290 can even hold itself up
on a hill but only if I buy it a present
first and if I do purchase the travel
electronics pack for 600 bucks
I also get smart phone pairing which is
one your human species is weak we'll
start on pavement so you can stop
screaming like a child
the 1290s power curve is extremely
linear it pulls hard pops the front
predictably at 5000 rpm and then keep
scrolling till you hit peak power just
shy of 9,000 then there's a low before
the limiter at 10,000 rpm so you
wouldn't find the glass ceiling unless
you went looking for it only problem is
the plank seat I mean it's great for
shifting my weight back and forth on the
dirt but with a hundred and sixty horses
in sport mode I feel like I'm going to
slide right off the thing there's a
quick shifter included with the
electronics upgrade so I can bang up
shifts with no regard for the clock and
good thing it works both ways because
slamming down shifts is much more
enjoyable than grabbing the Brembo
brakes with water because the initial
bite is pretty weak and also the
feedback not exactly encyclopedic the
handling is insanely sharp though I've
never felt pavement performance this
good on a 21 inch front wheel stiffer
fork springs result in the less nosedive
than the 1190 and Bosch cornering ABS
lets me yank believer mid turn without
tucking the front or standing the bike
up and running wide personally I'm
afraid I'll lose my braking skill both
can lever pressure and and manually
bouncing the front with rear input what
species is we doing yeah just like
school buses and tanks the KTM 1290 is
narrower than the R 1200 GS all my logic
tells me the BMW is still nimbler in the
twisties and I think it is but from
where I'm sitting the super adventure
feels sporty ER due to its smaller size
not as snappy as the old 1190 though
honestly this engine is a little bit too
linear on pavement and there's heaps of
power but it's all potatoes and no hot
sauce well shut up you know it's true
[Music]
hey I mean cheer up those sport your
smooth power delivery does make you a
great tour
I remember the 12 volt outlet and the
waterproof phone charging compartment
those are huge touring benefits and look
at your spacious organ omix I mean a 35
inch seat is going to do that for you
the aluminum handlebars the foot pegs
the shift lever the dash and the
windscreen are all adjustable too
although the latter moves in
emasculating two inches allegedly this
prevents my helmet from hitting the
windscreen which literally never happens
but I keep it low anyway because it
buffets less like this and it flows more
air the bodywork to also funnels more
wind to pass my torso the me old 1290
plus k GM put heat guards under the seat
so the header pipe only cooks my ass
medium-rare rather than the medium
welded to 1290 preferred and despite
containing pure hell fire engine somehow
keeps its heat to itself long story
short this 1290 is objectively cooler
than previous versions at least on a
summer's day other luxuries include
cornering LEDs which light around the
bend when the bike feels itself leaning
they're not as punctual as you might
expect initiate a turn and you'll notice
the beam catching up a second later but
hey I mean the thing is are brighter
than the Sun only touring letdown is the
throttle by wire return spring it's too
stiff and so it makes my wrist tired
after a while that and the 23 litre tank
which wouldn't be big enough for a bike
half this powerful I've been getting an
annoyingly short 250 kilometres before I
hit the 3.5 liter reserve oh nobody
criticisms transformer oh you look
exactly the same
ah right
this is a different machine limited to
100 horsepower it is world's more
manageable off-road mode also numbs the
throttle response so I no longer carved
the Grand Canyon within your engine
drift artificial intelligence run this
traction control it gives me the full
cocky rooster went upright but it wants
to digitally govern the power in the
turn I'm supposed to just slam the
throttle and let the bikes here with the
engine that feels very wrong to a
practice risk but don't try to outsmart
the machine because if you modulate the
throttle yourself the traction control
just gets pissed and understeers into a
ditch off-road abs is brilliant though
it unlinks the front and rear actuators
keeping a tight leash on the former
while letting me walk up the ladder the
electronic slipper clutch is also very
robotic
it measures rear wheel speed to detect
chatter and open the throttle
accordingly and it is creepily effective
and I can vomit downshift on the
slippery surfaces and get nothing which
is both amazing and a little bit
unnerving when you're counting on
backing the rear riding the 1290 fast
off-road isn't about trusting my skill
it's about trusting the computer skill
in transforming this bike for the dirt
that's a weird way to ride a motorcycle
to be honest the 1290 feels exactly like
what it is a big luxury motorcycle
that's been whipped and tortured and
because their behavior it's unnatural
and a little bit sad like a caged lion
you know what screw that and the SAR can
turn everything off on the fly give me a
160 horsepower no rider aids offroad
I'll try unleashing you one more time
with a bit of practice I can now see
that the chassis is brilliant
and it's so balanced and slim between
the legs that I'm actually doing this I
can actually ride 160 horsepower
off-road and hell it is intense the bike
gets it up like it runs on viagra by the
time the front wheel comes back down I'm
doing a hundred places I really
shouldn't be don't screw up now five
hundred and twenty-nine pound boots can
be a problem if I screw up picture
online pick the ticket buddy heaven
forbid I have to pick it up five hundred
thousand pounds with a Munich problems
on the big program but the bike feels
light when it moves it's up heavier Fork
Springs have it riding high in the
suspension stroke like a dirt bike the
knee point seven inch rear shock is a
progressive dual piston offering stiffer
compression near the end of travel so I
never bought them out don't watch the
rocks now trust your 9.8 inches ground
clearance and try to forget the KTM skip
the skid click just feather that clutch
it's a piece of straw an extremely light
pull to break the camel's back
slippery stuff at the end here no clutch
needed KTM added weight to the
crankshaft so the bike will carry itself
near idle just chug along at 1500 rpm no
drama no braking traction and a mouse
the 1290 is mechanically one of the top
three motorcycles in the world and it's
electronic intelligence is only
surpassed by its brother the S version
which touched down in Europe with semi
active suspension my frustration is
entirely my own I'm good enough to find
the digital age overbearing but not good
enough to master the enormous mechanical
potential without them
your human species is weak but I called
for backup a small board 4,000 dollars
cheaper 35 horsepower smaller and with
less computer-controlled
the enemy of the African twin is being
deployed now
you